Today we're going to be walking through how to use DeepSeek v3 in n8n
오늘은 n8n에서 DeepSeek v3를 사용하는 방법에 대해 알아보겠습니다.
for a fraction of what it costs to use something like GPT-4o or Claude 3.5 Sonnet.
GPT-4o나 Claude 3.5 Sonnet과 같은 모델을 사용하는 것보다 훨씬 저렴한 비용으로 말이죠.
But real quick, what is DeepSeek v3?
하지만 그 전에, DeepSeek v3가 무엇인지 간략히 짚고 넘어가겠습니다.
It's an open source model that was recently released
DeepSeek v3는 최근에 출시된 오픈소스 모델입니다.
and it pretty much outperforms every other open source model out there.
현존하는 다른 모든 오픈소스 모델들보다 뛰어난 성능을 보이고 있습니다.
And it also performs pretty comparable to the leading
또한, 선두적인 클로즈드 소스 모델인
closed source models like GPT-4o.
GPT-4o와 비교해도 뒤지지 않는 성능을 자랑합니다.
Now, I'm not an expert on models and fine tuning and training and all that kind of stuff,
저는 모델, 미세 조정, 훈련 등에 대한 전문가는 아닙니다.
but I've got a couple of graphics that I'll walk through here
하지만, 몇 가지 그래픽 자료를 통해 설명해 드리겠습니다.
and I'll also include the link to the technical report
그리고, 기술 보고서 링크도 설명란에 첨부해 드릴 테니,
in the description if you guys want to check it out for yourself.
직접 확인해 보셔도 좋습니다.
So as you can see right here in the blue,
여기 파란색으로 표시된 부분이 DeepSeek입니다.
And it's pretty much outperforming all of them in these six metrics.
DeepSeek는 이 여섯 가지 지표에서 다른 모든 모델들보다 우수한 성능을 보이고 있습니다.
But why did I decide to make this video and why did you probably click on it?
그렇다면, 제가 왜 이 영상을 제작하게 되었고, 여러분은 왜 이 영상을 클릭하셨을까요?
Because of the price.
바로 가격 때문입니다.
So as you can see here in the green, we've got $0.014 per million tokens.
여기 녹색으로 표시된 부분을 보면, 백만 토큰당 0.014달러라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
So you can just throw something like $2 in there and it's going to get you a really, really long way.
2달러 정도만 투자해도 정말 오랫동안 사용할 수 있는 양입니다.
Here's another graphic from that report that I was talking about.
앞서 언급했던 기술 보고서에 포함된 또 다른 그래픽을 보여드리겠습니다.
This is the needle in the haystack test.
이것은 '건초 더미에서 바늘 찾기' 테스트입니다.
As you can see, the whole board is green.
보시다시피, 전체가 녹색으로 표시되어 있습니다.
So, perfect 10 out of 10 score across everything.
즉, 모든 항목에서 10점 만점에 10점을 받았다는 의미입니다.
This basically tells us that DeepSeek v3 is really, really good with its context length
이는 DeepSeek v3가 컨텍스트 길이를 처리하는 데 매우 뛰어나다는 것을 보여줍니다.
and understanding everything that's going through and not
모든 내용을 이해하고, 다른 모델들처럼
missing out any information the way that some other models might.
정보를 놓치는 일이 없다는 것을 의미합니다.
So, something really interesting about DeepSeek
DeepSeek v3의 흥미로운 점은
v3 is that it uses a mixture of experts model.
혼합 전문가 모델(Mixture of Experts)을 사용한다는 것입니다.
Rather than having one model across all the parameters,
모든 매개변수에 대해 하나의 모델을 사용하는 대신,
this one has sub-models that it can sort of send out based on
특정 영역에 대한 전문 지식을 기반으로
expertise in certain areas, which is pretty cool.
하위 모델을 선택적으로 활용하는 방식입니다.
Once again, it's not something I fully understand as far as all the technicalities.
다시 한번 말씀드리지만, 저도 모든 기술적인 내용을 완벽하게 이해하는 것은 아닙니다.
Go check out that report if you want to read more about it.
자세한 내용은 기술 보고서를 참고해 주시기 바랍니다.
But this isn't me recommending that it's
이것은 제가 DeepSeek v3가 더 낫다고 추천하거나, 사용을 권장하는 것은 아닙니다.
And of course, you should be careful with the data that you're putting into something like DeepSeek v3.
물론, DeepSeek v3와 같은 모델에 데이터를 입력할 때는 신중해야 합니다.
But I just kind of wanted to bring you the facts of what I know and
저는 단지 제가 알고 있는 사실과 n8n에 연결하는 방법,
how to actually plug it into n8n and just get in there and play around with it a little bit.
그리고, 직접 사용해 보면서 느낀 점들을 전달해 드리고 싶었을 뿐입니다.
So, let's get into n8n.
이제 n8n으로 넘어가 보겠습니다.
So, today I'm going to be talking about two ways to connect DeepSeek v3 into n8n.
오늘은 DeepSeek v3를 n8n에 연결하는 두 가지 방법을 소개하겠습니다.
So, the first one is hooking it up as the brain for your AI agent.
첫 번째는 AI 에이전트의 두뇌, 즉 챗 모델로 연결하는 것입니다.
The chat model for your AI agent.
AI 에이전트의 챗 모델로 사용하는 것입니다.
As you can see right here, it looks like we're connecting to an OpenAI chat model.
여기서는 OpenAI 챗 모델에 연결하는 것처럼 보이지만,
But if you click in, you can see that we're actually using
자세히 보면 실제로는
an OpenRouter base URL to point us to DeepSeek chat.
OpenRouter의 기본 URL을 사용하여 DeepSeek 챗으로 연결하고 있습니다.
So, that's what's going on here.
이게 첫 번째 방법입니다.
And then the second way is to use it as sort of its own node,
두 번째 방법은 DeepSeek v3를 독립적인 노드로 사용하는 것입니다.
like a OpenAI message and model node.
마치 OpenAI의 메시지 및 모델 노드처럼 말이죠.
So, as you can see here, we're doing a post request to DeepSeek
여기서는 DeepSeek에 POST 요청을 보내고,
and we're sending in information for it to come back with a response.
정보를 전달하여 응답을 받는 방식입니다.
So, I'll real quickly show off these two methods and then we'll get into how you actually do it.
이제 이 두 가지 방법을 간략히 시연해 본 후, 실제로 어떻게 설정하는지 설명해 드리겠습니다.
So, first we'll do this one.
먼저, 이 방법부터 시연해 보겠습니다.
As you can see here, it's a post request to DeepSeek.
여기 보시는 것처럼, DeepSeek에 POST 요청을 보내고 있습니다.
We have our stuff that I'll show you guys how to configure.
설정 방법은 잠시 후에 자세히 설명해 드리겠습니다.
And then pretty much in here, what we're asking it to do is we're sending,
여기서는 "다음 주제에 대한 페이스북 게시물을 작성해 줘"라는 요청을 보내고 있습니다.
write me a Facebook post about the following topic.
주제는 동적으로 설정되며,
The topic's dynamic based on what we put into this set node right here,
여기 이 노드에 입력한 값에 따라 결정됩니다.
which is health and fitness in 2025.
지금은 "2025년의 건강과 피트니스"로 설정되어 있습니다.
So, let's fire this off real quick.
그럼, 한번 실행해 보겠습니다.
As you can see, it's hitting DeepSeek and then it's going to come back to us with a result,
DeepSeek에 요청을 보내고, 응답을 기다립니다.
which should be a formatted Facebook post
응답은 이모티콘과 해시태그가 포함된 형식의 페이스북 게시물일 것입니다.
As you can see, health and fitness, the future is here.
보시다시피, "건강과 피트니스, 미래가 여기에 있습니다"라는 제목과 함께
It's got a couple points and then it ends with a nice little motivational message.
몇 가지 내용이 있고, 마지막에는 동기 부여 메시지로 마무리됩니다.
And if this is confusing to you,
이 부분이 헷갈리실 수도 있지만,
it's the exact same way that you would set up an OpenAI message and model node.
OpenAI의 메시지 및 모델 노드를 설정하는 것과 정확히 동일한 방식입니다.
And you've probably done that multiple times.
아마 여러분은 이미 여러 번 해보셨을 겁니다.
You've got a system role right here, which is
여기 시스템 역할은 이 노드가 무엇을 할지 정의하는 것입니다.
We're just saying you're a helpful assistant.
"당신은 도움이 되는 어시스턴트입니다"라고 설정했습니다.
And then we have the actual user role, which is what we want it to take and do,
그리고, 사용자 역할은 이 노드에 무엇을 시킬지, 즉 우리가 원하는 작업을 정의합니다.
which is writing a Facebook post about health and fitness in 2025.
여기서는 "2025년의 건강과 피트니스에 대한 페이스북 게시물 작성"을 요청하고 있습니다.
So, if that's confusing, just look at it like this, right?
이 부분이 헷갈리신다면, 이렇게 생각하시면 됩니다.
In OpenAI, usually you're set up your different messages.
OpenAI에서는 일반적으로 여러 메시지를 설정합니다. 시스템 역할과 사용자 역할이 있습니다.
So, right here, helpful assistant, write me a Facebook post.
여기서는 "도움이 되는 어시스턴트", "페이스북 게시물 작성"이라고 설정했습니다.
And it's pretty much the exact same thing coming through.
그리고, 이 두 가지는 거의 동일한 방식으로 작동합니다.
So, that's pretty much all that's going on here.
차이점을 보여드리기 위해 완료될 때까지 기다리겠습니다.
I just wanted to let this finish so we could see the difference.
이 부분은 완료될 때까지 기다려서 차이점을 보여드리겠습니다.
There we go. So, this was using 4o.
완료되었습니다. 이것은 4o를 사용한 결과입니다.
And this one, again, is
그리고, 이 결과는
a little bit different because it uses a different model, but same aspect of Facebook post.
다른 모델을 사용했기 때문에 약간 다르지만, 페이스북 게시물이라는 동일한 목적을 가지고 있습니다.
Anyways, now we'll come up here and we'll pretty much do that same thing.
이제 위쪽 예시를 실행해 보겠습니다.
So... this is connected to...
이 예시는 DeepSeek v3에 연결되어 있습니다.
what's it called? DeepSeek v3. And we'll do the same thing.
DeepSeek v3에 연결해서, 동일한 요청을 해보겠습니다.
Make a Facebook post
페이스북 게시물 작성
about health and fitness 2025.
2025년 건강과 피트니스
And... okay.
그리고...
So, we actually didn't connect our credential real quick.
자격 증명을 연결하지 않았었네요.
We were connected to our OpenAI account, but as you can see, I have a different credential here,
이전에는 OpenAI 계정에 연결되어 있었지만, 지금은 DeepSeek 자격 증명을 사용하고 있습니다.
which is the DeepSeek one. So, I'll show you guys how to set this up.
자격 증명 설정 방법은 잠시 후에 설명해 드리겠습니다.
But now this should work fine.
이제 정상적으로 작동할 것입니다.
Let's go back in here, send that off.
다시 돌아가서, 요청을 보내 보겠습니다.
And I know it's a little confusing because it looks like it's still an OpenAI chat model,
여전히 OpenAI 챗 모델처럼 보여서 헷갈릴 수 있지만,
but like I said, all we have to do is grab an API key from OpenRouter
앞서 말씀드렸듯이, OpenRouter에서 API 키를 가져오기만 하면
and then we'll be good to go to set everything up.
모든 설정을 완료할 수 있습니다.
Okay. There we go.
네, 됐습니다.
So, now we got our Facebook post back.
이제 페이스북 게시물이 생성되었습니다.
Very similar with its
이전 예시와 매우 유사하게
hashtags at the end, with its different emojis for different sections.
마지막에 해시태그가 있고, 각 섹션에 이모티콘이 사용되었습니다.
And yeah.
네, 됐습니다.
So, those are the two use cases that we're going to walk over real quick.
지금까지 두 가지 사용 사례를 간략히 살펴보았습니다.
So, let's hop into DeepSeek and set everything up.
이제 DeepSeek를 설정하는 방법을 알아보겠습니다.
Okay. So, you're going to go to DeepSeek.com.
먼저, DeepSeek.com에 접속합니다.
You'll come into this screen. You'll sign in or you'll create an account.
이 화면에서 로그인하거나 계정을 생성합니다.
And then you're going to click on access API.
그리고, "Access API"를 클릭합니다.
So, this is going to take you straight to your API settings. So,
그러면 API 설정 페이지로 이동합니다.
it took me to my usage. As you can see, I put in $2.
저는 사용량 페이지로 이동되었습니다. 보시다시피, 저는 2달러를 충전했습니다.
I've got over 7 million tokens.
7백만 개 이상의 토큰을 사용할 수 있습니다.
You're going to click on API keys, create new key.
"API keys"를 클릭하고, "create new key"를 클릭합니다.
We'll call this one demo.
이름을 "demo"로 지정하겠습니다.
And then you want to copy that and paste it somewhere safe
그리고, 생성된 API 키를 복사해서 안전한 곳에 붙여넣으세요.
because you won't be able to re-access it.
나중에 다시 볼 수 없기 때문입니다.
And you could always just create a new one, but
물론, 새 키를 다시 생성할 수도 있지만,
best practice is to paste it somewhere safe.
안전한 곳에 붙여넣는 것이 가장 좋습니다.
Then you need to make sure you have some tokens available. So, just add in like $2.
이제 사용 가능한 토큰이 있는지 확인해야 합니다. 2달러 정도 충전하세요.
And then you want to click on docs down here on the left side.
그리고, 왼쪽 하단의 "docs"를 클릭합니다.
This is going to bring you to this API documentation.
그러면 API 문서 페이지로 이동합니다.
And all you have to do is scroll down right here. We've got a curl.
아래로 스크롤하면 curl 예시가 있습니다.
We're going to copy this curl
이 curl을 복사합니다.
and it's going to be super easy. We'll hop back into n8n.
이제 n8n으로 돌아가서 붙여넣기만 하면 됩니다.
As you can see, there's currently no DeepSeek integration.
현재 n8n에는 DeepSeek 통합 기능이 없습니다.
So, what we have to do is grab an HTTP request.
따라서, HTTP 요청 노드를 사용해야 합니다.
And all we have to do is import curl and paste that right in there.
"import curl"을 클릭하고, 방금 복사한 curl을 붙여넣습니다.
So, as you can see, it's going to change it to a post request.
그러면 POST 요청으로 자동 변경됩니다.
It put in the correct endpoint
올바른 엔드포인트가 입력되었고,
and has our header already, which is our authorization.
인증 정보가 포함된 헤더도 자동으로 입력되었습니다.
And then it has our JSON already filled out. So, super easy.
그리고, JSON 데이터도 이미 채워져 있습니다. 매우 간편합니다.
Now, what you want to do is you got to go grab that API key.
이제, 앞서 복사해 둔 API 키를 가져와야 합니다.
And then you want to get rid of this.
그리고, 이 부분을 삭제합니다.
It's going to be bearer space your API key.
"Bearer" 다음에 공백을 하나 넣고, API 키를 붙여넣습니다.
And then make sure there's no extra leading or trailing white space as well.
그리고, 앞뒤에 불필요한 공백이 없도록 주의해야 합니다.
And that should work.
이제 정상적으로 작동할 것입니다.
So, right now, what we're sending over is the prompt is hello to a helpful assistant.
현재 "도움이 되는 어시스턴트에게 hello"라는 프롬프트를 보내고 있습니다.
We'll just hit test step to make sure everything's working.
"test step"을 클릭하여 모든 것이 정상적으로 작동하는지 확인해 보겠습니다.
And as you can see, we got back, hello, how can I assist you today?
"안녕하세요, 오늘 무엇을 도와드릴까요?"라는 응답을 받았습니다.
So, it was responding to the message, which was hello.
"hello"라는 메시지에 대한 응답입니다.
So, that's pretty much it.
설정은 거의 다 끝났습니다.
At this point, you would set up, you know, you could prompt
이제 이 DeepSeek 노드에
this deep seek node a little differently if you wanted it to do something more specific.
다른 프롬프트를 설정하여, 더 구체적인 작업을 수행하도록 만들 수 있습니다.
And then you could dynamically give the information that you want it to respond to.
그리고, 응답을 원하는 정보를 동적으로 제공할 수 있습니다.
Okay. Now, to set up a chat model.
이제 챗 모델을 설정해 보겠습니다.
So, let's delete this one.
이 노드는 삭제하겠습니다.
We're going to add another one, which is an OpenAI chat model.
OpenAI 챗 모델 노드를 추가하겠습니다.
And this is like the default way that it pretty much opens up.
이것은 기본적으로 열리는 방식입니다.
And we need to create a new credential.
새 자격 증명을 생성해야 합니다.
But before that, we need to set up everything with open router.
하지만 그 전에, OpenRouter에서 모든 것을 설정해야 합니다.
So, we're going to click add option.
"add option"을 클릭합니다.
We're going to add a base URL.
"base URL"을 추가합니다.
Default, of course, it points to OpenAI because that's the model we're grabbing.
기본적으로는 OpenAI를 가리키고 있지만, 이것은 우리가 가져오려는 모델이기 때문입니다.
But we're going to go to open router.
이제 OpenRouter로 이동합니다.
You'll create an account.
계정을 생성합니다.
And then all we need to do is go to deep seek v3.
그리고, DeepSeek v3를 찾습니다.
What we want to do here is click on API.
여기서 "API"를 클릭합니다.
And we're looking for a base URL to point to, to grab deep seek.
DeepSeek를 가져오기 위해 가리킬 기본 URL을 찾아야 합니다.
So, we're going to grab this right here.
여기 이 부분을 복사합니다.
Base URL within the quotations.
따옴표 안의 기본 URL을 복사합니다.
Copy that.
다시 n8n으로 돌아갑니다.
Go back into n8n.
여기에 붙여넣습니다. 이제
Paste that in there. So, now we're
OpenRouter의 기본 URL에 접근하고 있습니다.
accessing the base URL of open router.
그리고, 위쪽에서 GPT-4o mini 대신,
And then up here, instead of accessing GPT-4o mini,
또는 사용 중인 다른 모델 대신, "expression"을 선택합니다. 기존 모델명을 지웁니다.
You're going to get rid of that.
다시 OpenRouter로 돌아갑니다.
Go back into open router.
DeepSeek v3 페이지인지 확인합니다.
And make sure you're on deep seek v3.
여기 이 부분을 복사합니다.
You're going to copy that right here.
모델명을 복사합니다. DeepSeek/deepseek-chat
And then you're going to paste that in there.
그리고, 여기에 붙여넣습니다.
So, now we're pointing to open router URL, which is grabbing this model of deep seek.
이제 OpenRouter URL을 통해 DeepSeek의 이 모델에 접근하고 있습니다.
And now before we...
이제,
Hit out of here. We need to create new credentials.
나가기 전에, 새 자격 증명을 생성해야 합니다.
So, you can see I've got a deep seek credential. I'm going to create a new one.
보시다시피, 저는 DeepSeek 자격 증명을 가지고 있습니다. 새 자격 증명을 생성해 보겠습니다.
But first, we need to create an API key.
하지만, 먼저 API 키를 생성해야 합니다.
So, you're already in this page.
이미 이 페이지에 있습니다.
You're going to click create API key.
"create API key"를 클릭합니다.
You're going to create key.
"create a key"를 클릭합니다.
Name it whatever you want.
원하는 이름으로 지정합니다.
And then same thing as always.
그리고, 앞서와 마찬가지로
Copy this into somewhere safe.
이 키를 안전한 곳에 복사해 둡니다.
And then you're pretty much just going to go back into n8n.
그리고, n8n으로 돌아갑니다.
Hit create new credential.
"create new credential"을 클릭합니다.
And paste your API key right into here.
그리고, 여기에 API 키를 붙여넣습니다.
Once you do that, you're going to hit save.
그런 다음, "save"를 클릭합니다.
In the bottom right, it's going to go green and say, So it's currently private to you
오른쪽 하단에 "현재 여러분에게 비공개입니다"라는 녹색 메시지가 뜹니다.
and right here it's going to go red.
그리고, 여기는 빨간색으로 변합니다.
Not exactly sure why it does that, but
왜 그런지 정확히는 모르겠지만,
you're connected if you get the green down here.
아래쪽에 녹색 메시지가 뜨면 연결된 것입니다.
That might just be a bug, but we're good to go.
버그일 수도 있지만, 어쨌든 연결은 완료되었습니다.
So we've got our API key from OpenRouter set up right here.
OpenRouter에서 생성한 API 키가 여기에 설정되었습니다.
We have the DeepSeek model that we want,
사용하려는 DeepSeek 모델을 선택했고,
and then we have OpenRouter being able to access this model for us.
OpenRouter가 이 모델에 접근할 수 있도록 설정했습니다.
So now we just want to test to make sure it's working.
이제 정상적으로 작동하는지 테스트해 보겠습니다.
We're going to open up a chat and we'll do this again, but instead of health and fitness,
채팅을 열고, 다시 한번 테스트해 보겠습니다. 이번에는 "건강과 피트니스" 대신 "스포츠"로
what it says here.
설정해 보겠습니다.
And as you can see, it's hitting the model right now, which is obviously DeepSeek,
보시다시피, 현재 DeepSeek 모델에 요청을 보내고 있습니다.
even though it looks like OpenAI.
OpenAI처럼 보이지만 말이죠.
And we know that it's working because it would have already failed by now if we didn't have it set up.
그리고, 정상적으로 작동한다는 것을 알 수 있습니다. 설정이 잘못되었다면 이미 실패했을 테니까요.
As you saw earlier, it failed really quick.
앞서 보셨듯이, 설정이 잘못되면 매우 빠르게 실패합니다.
Okay, so it just popped through.
네, 응답이 도착했습니다.
We've got sports in 2025 where innovation meets passion.
"혁신과 열정이 만나는 2025년의 스포츠"라는 제목과 함께,
Again, emojis, little things.
이모티콘과 내용이 보입니다.
And remember, this is zero prompting at all, but then it ends with some hashtags.
그리고, 여기에는 전혀 프롬프트 엔지니어링을 하지 않았지만, 마지막에 해시태그로 마무리됩니다.
But yeah, like I said, there's no prompting going on in here.
하지만, 말씀드렸듯이, 여기에는 어떠한 프롬프트 엔지니어링도 적용되지 않았습니다.
But this is, of course, the chat input that I got and our output.
이것은 제가 입력한 채팅 내용이고, 그에 대한 결과입니다.
So that's pretty much going to be it for this one.
이번 영상은 여기서 마무리하겠습니다.
I know it wasn't too complex, but I just wanted to show you guys how you can access this stuff
그렇게 복잡한 내용은 아니었지만, 여러분들이 직접 사용해 볼 수 있도록
so you can get in there and start playing around with it.
이러한 기능들을 어떻게 활용할 수 있는지 보여드리고 싶었습니다.
I'm definitely going to play around with a little bit more, some complex agents
저는 앞으로 DeepSeek 모델을 사용해서
with our DeepSeek model and just seeing how it reacts to them
좀 더 복잡한 에이전트를 만들어보고,
using different tools and stuff.
다양한 도구들을 사용했을 때 어떻게 반응하는지 살펴볼 계획입니다.
But two credits in DeepSeek, five credits in OpenRouter.
DeepSeek에 2 크레딧, OpenRouter에 5 크레딧을 사용해 보세요.
In OpenRouter, you have a ton of different models you can access as well,
OpenRouter에서는 다양한 모델을 사용할 수 있습니다.
but those credits will get you a long way for sure. But yeah, as always, if you found this one helpful,
이 정도 크레딧이면 충분히 오랫동안 사용할 수 있을 것입니다. 이번 영상이 도움이 되셨다면, 좋아요를 눌러주세요. 정말 큰 힘이 됩니다.
please give it a like, definitely helps me out.
영상이 도움 되었다면, 좋아요를 꼭 눌러주세요. 정말 큰 힘이 됩니다.
Great to be back.
다시 돌아오게 되어 기쁩니다.
Hope you guys all had a happy new year.
여러분 모두 새해 복 많이 받으셨기를 바랍니다.
I'm really excited to see what 2025 brings as far as the channel,
제 채널과 AI 분야 등 모든 면에서 2025년이 어떤 한 해가 될지 정말 기대됩니다.
the AI space, all that kind of stuff.
AI 분야를 포함해서, 모든 것들에 있어서, 2025년이 어떤 모습일지 정말 기대됩니다.
And definitely let me know in the comments what else you guys are looking to see
앞으로 몇 주, 몇 달, 그리고, 내년에 어떤 영상들을 보고 싶으신지 댓글로 남겨주세요.
in the next few weeks, in the next few months, and in the next year.
앞으로 몇 주, 몇 달, 그리고 내년에 어떤 영상들을 보고 싶으신지 댓글로 남겨주세요.
So thanks for making it to the end of this one, guys.
끝까지 시청해 주셔서 감사합니다.